Guide to the Robert Preston Harriss Papers, 1913-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert Preston Harriss papers 1913-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harriss, Robert Preston
10.4 linear feet Extent: Approximately 7800 Items
Journalist, arts critic and author of Baltimore, Maryland. Collection spans the years 1913-1989 and includes correspondence; autobiographical information on Harriss; clippings (including Harriss' writings); printed material (menus, programs, press releases, travel brochures, itineraries, and maps); biographical sketches of associates and artists; photographs and slides; ledgers containing articles and reviews on music, ballet, opera and the stage; tear sheets; and audiovisual material. Individuals sending letters or referred to in the materials include Gerald W. Johnson, Sara Mayfield, Lizette Woods Reese, August Mencken, H. L. Mencken, Robert Minford, Eugene Ormandy, Art Buchwald, and Harriss's sister, Ruth Tyson, among others.
RL.00516
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research with the exception of a manuscript in Box 44, which is closed to use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies must be made before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert Preston Harriss Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1973 to 1990.
Collection Overview
The Robert Preston Harriss Papers span the years 1913-1989 and consist of the following materials: professional and personal correspondence; an autobiography of Robert ("Robin") Preston Harriss and a description of his early life in Fayetteville and the Cape Fear Valley, N.C.; clippings (including his articles for the Baltimore Magazine and the Baltimore Sun); printed material (menus, programs, press releases, travel brochures, itineraries, and maps); biographical sketches of associates and artists; photographs and slides; ledgers containing articles and reviews on music, ballet, opera and the stage; tear sheets; audiovisual material, chiefly interviews of Harriss; and transcriptions of an interview of Harriss by Lawrence Angle. Includes material relating to Harriss' career as editor of the periodical Gardens, Houses, and People (1947-1957). A run of issues of Gardens, Houses, and People from the same years was transferred to Perkins Library's Periodicals Department at processing. Writings in the collection by Harriss also come from the Baltimore American, the Frederick News-Post, and the Baltimore News-American. Individuals with significant letters, significant amounts of correspondence, or referred to in other materials include Gerald W. Johnson, Sara Mayfield, August Mencken, H. L. Mencken (two boxes of material), Robert Minford, Eugene Ormandy, Lizette Woodworth Reese, and Harriss' sister, Ruth Tyson. Correspondence from his sister gives details on life in Fayetteville, N.C., including a description of the time period during World War I and the effects of the Spanish influenza epidemic. There are lesser amounts of materials on other individuals as well in the author subject files. One of Harriss' manuscript drafts is currently closed to access. Original recordings are closed to use; viewing or listening copies must be made before contents can be accessed.
Subject Headings
Art critics -- Maryland; Baltimore (Md.) -- Intellectual life; Cape Fear River Valley (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Fayetteville (N.C.) -- History; Harriss, Robert Preston; Johnson, Gerald W. (Gerald White), 1890-1980; Journalists -- Correspondence; Journalists -- Maryland -- Baltimore; Maryland -- Newspapers; Mayfield, Sara, 1905-; Mencken, August, 1889-1967; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Minford, Robert; Ormandy, Eugene, 1899-1985; Performing arts -- United States -- Reviews; Reese, Lizette Woodworth, 1856-1935; Tyson, Ruth
Related Material
Oral History Collection: OH.8221 ROBERT PRESTON ("ROBIN")HARRISS (fl.1926-78) Baltimore Symphony Series, 1977. Interviewer: Alfred Kohnsky 1977; 1 p. 50 minutes.
Maryland Historical Society.
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1925-1982, (11 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 9)
  - Family correspondence, 1925-1981 (Box 10)
  - Ruth Harriss Tyson correspondence, 1941-1981 (Box 11)
- Artwork Series, (1 box)
  - Drawings (Box 12)
  - Editorial art (Box 12)
- Clippings Series, 1935-1980s and undated, (2 boxes)
  - A-O (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1980s (Box 14)
  - Notebook of clippings, 1987-1988 (Box 14)
- Memorabilia Series, (1 box)
  - Memorabilia files (Box 15)
- Miscellany Series, (10 boxes)
  Subject files on individuals contain mixed material, including correspondence.
  - Brazil (Box 15)
  - Brochures and leaflets (Box 16)
  - Christmas cards (Box 16)
  - Invitations (Box 16)
  - Meet the Authors, mottoes, posters (Box 17)
  - Leonard Bahr (Box 18)
  - Leon Bonvin (Box 18)
  - Brian Fried (Box 18)
  - Grace Hartigan (Box 18)
  - Winni Hender (Box 18)
  - Gerald W. Johnson (Box 18)
  - A. and T. Klots (Box 19)
  - Raymond Lark (Box 19)
  - Jacques Maroger (Box 19)
  - Sara Mayfield (Box 19)
  - Eugene Ormandy (Box 19)
  - Ezra Pound (Box 19)
  - Curt Richter (Box 19)
  - Paul Robeson (Box 19)
  - Joseph St. Lawrence (Box 19)
  - Joseph Sheppard, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Aaron Sopher (Box 20)
  - Betty Wells (Box 20)
  - R. A. Yeardley (Box 20)
  - Memorabilia (Box 22)
  - Mencken, Henry Louis (Box 37-38)
  - Mencken, August (Box 38)
  - Reese, Lizette Woodworth (Box 39)
- Photographs Series, (1 box)
  - Includes slides and photographs relating to Harriss' professional life and contacts. (Box 21)
- Writings Series, (6 boxes)
  - Writings (Box 23)
  - Writings, manuscripts, Not All Magnolia: A Tarheel Boyhood (Box 24)
  - Writings, manuscripts, Out of This Clay (Box 25)
  - Writings, various authors, Exiles from Paradise (Box 26)
  - Biography (Box 12)
  - Two Harriss handwritten manuscripts: The Strange Case of Donald Watts, a short character sketch (restriction lifted in 1991); and another character sketch (closed to use) (Box 44)
- Printed Material Series, (8 boxes)
  - Miscellany (Box 27)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art (Box 27)
  - Art (Box 28)
  - Walters Art Gallery (Box 28)
  - Dance (Box 29-30)
  - Drama (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 32)
  - Music (Box 33)
  - Volumes (Box 34)
- Volumes Series, 1959-1974, (2 boxes)
  - Clippings related to music (including ballet and opera) and drama, 1959-1967 (Box 35)
  - Clippings related to music (including ballet and opera) and drama, 1968-1974 (Box 36)
- Audiovisual Material Series, (4 boxes)
  [Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Listening or viewing copies must be made before contents can be accessed for research.]
  - Recordings (audio reels) (Box 40)
  - Other audiovisual material (Box 41-43)
- Oversize Material, 1939-1985, (12 boxes)
  Consists mainly of tearsheets of Preston Harriss arts columns from various newspapers, chiefly the Baltimore News American and the Frederick News-Post.
  - Various newspapers, 1939-1956, (3 folders) (Box 45)
  - Baltimore News American, 1948-1959, (2 folders) (Box 45)
  - Frederick News-Post, 1957-1963, (5 folders) (Box 45)
  - Various newspapers, 1961-1964, (6 folders) (Box 46)
  - Baltimore News American, 1963-1967, (3 folders) (Box 46)
  - Various newspapers, 1964-1976, (1 folder) (Box 46)
  - Baltimore News American, 1965-1989, (6 folders) (Box 47)
  - Baltimore News American, 1967-1970, (11 folders) (Box 48)
  - Baltimore News American, 1969-1971, (12 folders) (Box 49)
  - Baltimore News American, 1971-1973, (13 folders) (Box 50)
  - Baltimore News American, 1974-1975, (13 folders) (Box 51)
  - Baltimore News American, 1974-1976, (9 folders) (Box 52)
  - Baltimore News American, 1976-1978, (11 folders) (Box 53)
  - Baltimore News American, 1977-1979, (4 folders) (Box 54)
  - Various newspapers, 1978-1979, (7 folders) (Box 54)
  - Baltimore News American, 1979-1981, (6 folders) (Box 55)
  - Various newspapers, 1981-1982, (4 folders) (Box 55)
  - Baltimore News American, 1982-1985, (4 folders) (Box 56)
  - Various newspapers, 1986-1988, (2 folders) (Box 56)
  - Miscellaneous art and invitations (Oversize-box 6)
  - Musical scores (Oversize-box 6)
- Accession (90-042), (1 box)
  - Video interview of Harriss and transcript (Box 1)